中文字幕來源：bilibili
英文字幕來源：iPlayer
OCR/雙語合并/調軸：James丶xz
刪減字幕翻譯補齊：Hodoscope
9號秘事
第七季   第六集
今天是我妹妹的生日
It's my sister's birthday today.
我6歲了
I'm six!
她得到了一個新的風箏
She got a new kite.
我答應媽媽
I promised Mummy
去外面玩風箏時 我會照顧好妹妹的
I would watch her while we played with it outside.
該我玩了
It's my turn now.
這是我的生日禮物
No, it's my present
我想自己放風箏
and I want to fly it.
別哭 它在上面呢 看
Don't cry. I can see it up there. Look.
太高了
It's very high.
有電危險
沒關系 我能爬上去的
That's all right. I can climb up.
傻瓜 傻瓜
Twit-you. Twit-you!
你好 聰明的貓頭鷹
Hello, Wise Owl.
傻瓜
Twit-you.
只有傻瓜才會爬上去
Only a fool would climb up there.
你們沒看到警告牌嗎
Didn't you see the warning sign?
有電危險
Pylons kill.
別靠近這里
Stay away from them.
我不會碰電線的
I won't touch the wires.
有電危險
那也不行
That doesn't matter.
風箏的金屬線是可以導電的
The electricity will be conducted through the kite's metal rods.
那我的風箏怎么辦
But what about my present?
看我們的風朋友能不能幫忙了
Let's see if our friend the wind can help.
有電危險
謝謝你 聰明的貓頭鷹
Thanks, Wise Owl!
Thanks, Wise Owl.
別做傻瓜
Don't be a twit-you.
不要觸電
Leave electricity alone.
不要                     觸電
聰明的貓頭鷹
傻瓜 傻瓜
Twit-you. Twit-you!
哦 你好 是奧利弗先生嗎
Oh, hello. Is that Mr Oliver?
我是德雷克·布蘭肯 住在鹿場那邊
It's Derek Blenkin here. I live on Deerfold.
去年你給我鄰居的短尾狗做過標本
You did my neighbour's bobtail last year.
他叫佩珀醫生
Dr Pepper.
抱歉 我是不是找錯了
Sorry, have I got the right house?
你是做標本的嗎
You do do taxidermy?
嗯 是這么回事
Right. Well, what it is,
我們剛剛度假回來
we've just come back off our holidays
安排了清潔工
and we'd left our cleaner
來喂我女兒的寵物兔子 法拉利
to feed our daughter's pet rabbit, Ferrari.
法拉利是那只兔子 不是我女兒
That's the rabbit, not me daughter.
她想給它喂點好吃的
Anyway, she wanted to give it a treat,
長話短說吧
and to cut a long story sideways,
她不小心喂了它一袋巧克力
she's accidentally fed it a bag of chocolate buttons
然后兔子就死了
and now it's dead.
你在聽嗎
Are you there?
我不該和陌生人說話
I'm not supposed to talk to strangers.
其實
Well, um...
我們把它放在冰箱里凍了一宿
..we've had it in the fridge overnight.
我女兒還不知道 她才五歲
My daughter doesn't know yet. She's only five.
你能不能把它做成標本
And I was wondering if you could preserve him for us?
法拉利
Ferrari.
她不會看出來的
She won't know the difference.
我會跟她說兔子累了
I'll just tell her it's always tired.
我鄰居說你的要價比較便宜
My neighbour said you'd do us a good price.
你不用把它弄得
I don't need it all dressed up
像彼得兔那么漂亮
and doing ballet like a Beatrix Potter.
我會把它藏在鋪著稻草的角落里
It'll just be in the corner of the hutch covered in straw.
基本上沒人會看到它
You'll barely see it.
我們只是還沒想好
It's just...we're not ready
怎么和她聊死亡的話題
for the whole death conversation yet.
倒是該跟我媽聊聊了
We've got all that to come with my mother.
哦 非常感謝
Oh, thanks very much.
我說了 給個折扣就行
As I say, any discount gratefully received. And...
而且要是能便宜的話 沒有腿也行
..It needn't even have legs if that's cheaper.
那就這樣
OK.
很高興認識你
Nice to meet you too.
假期里有一天天氣特別好
One day on our holidays the weather was so nice
我們就來到了海邊
we came to the beach.
我想去海里游泳
I want to go in the sea.
媽媽帶妹妹去劃船了
Mummy took my sister paddling
我開始挖沙造城堡
and I started to make a sandcastle.
正玩得高興
I was happy playing,
有個人過來跟我說話
when a man came to talk to me.
他說我長得可愛又陽光
He said I looked nice and shiny,
問我想不想去看海星
and did I want to see a starfish?
我覺得挺好玩的
I thought that sounded fun.
傻瓜 傻瓜
Twit-you. Twit-you!
你不認識這個人
You don't know who this man is.
他或許看上去很友善
He may seem friendly
可未必有好心
but his intentions might not be.
你媽媽是怎么說陌生人的
What did your mummy tell you about strangers?
別跟陌生人說話
That I shouldn't talk to them?
沒錯
Exactly.
別當傻瓜
Don't be a twit-you.
別離開爸爸媽媽身邊
Always stay safe with your mummy and daddy.
聰明的貓頭鷹什么都知道
Wise Owl knows best.
媽媽
Mummy...
Mummy!
媽媽
聰明的貓頭鷹先生
請郵遞員先生把信送給聰明的貓頭鷹
今天是我妹妹的生日
It's my sister's birthday today.
我6歲了
I'm six!
她得到了一個娃娃
She got a doll,
一套茶具 還有一個風箏
a tea set and a kite.
現在就等媽媽回來
Now we're waiting for Mummy to get home
給她點生日蛋糕上的蠟燭了
so we can light the candles on her cake.
我現在就想點
I want to do it now.
我知道火柴在哪里
I know where they keep the matches.
看
Look!
安全火柴
你好 媽媽
Hi, Mum.
羅尼
Ronnie?
我都要睡了
I'm getting ready for bed.
現在才8點一刻
It's only quarter past eight.
我正喝酒呢 想起給你打個電話
I'm calling you between Corries.
你還好吧
Are you all right?
我挺好的
Yeah.
我去找過你 但你不在
I came round earlier. You weren't in.
我去忙了
I've been busy.
我要把一只兔子做成標本
I had to stuff a Ferrari.
一只什么
A what?
就是別人的寵物
It's someone's pet.
我們養過一只貓 你還記得嗎
We had a cat, do you remember?
你和喬安妮小時候養的
when you and Joanne were little.
叫米姆西
Mimsy.
我們最后把它處理掉了
We got rid of it in the end.
它讓你得了哮喘
It made you wheeze.
它看你的眼神很輕蔑
And it had this way of looking at you all superior,
感覺你就像是它鞋子上的塵土
like you were just muck on its shoe.
貓是不穿鞋的
Cats don't wear shoes.
你明白我在說什么就行了
Well, you know what I mean.
我就是想確認一下
Anyway I'm just checking
你星期一還過來嗎
that you're still coming on Monday.
你已經有三年沒回家了
You haven't been in over three years.
迪內托大夫的話還記得吧
You know what Dr Dinetto said.
他又不認識我
He doesn't know me.
他什么都不知道
He doesn't know anything.
我能照顧好自己的
I can look after myself.
我知道你行的 我就是希望你能回家來
I know you can. I'd just like you to be there,
僅此而已 為了我
that's all. For me.
穿靴子的貓 穿上靴子就得
Puss in Boots, he wore shoes, so...
我爸會在嗎
Will Dad be there?
不知道
I'm not sure.
我問過他 可他大概不會來吧
I asked him, but he might not show up.
你知道他就那樣
You know what he's like.
估計你也沒和他聯系吧
I don't suppose you've heard from him?
我們都是按自己的方式做事 是吧
We all deal with things in our own way, don't we?
答應我一定要回來
Promise me you'll come.
好的
OK.
還有 回來之前別干傻事
And you won't...do anything silly before then?
答應我
Promise?
答應你了
Promise.
那就好 我明天再給你打電話 親愛的
All right, then, I'll call you tomorrow, sweetheart.
再見
Bye.
我愛
I love...
今天是她生日
It was her birthday.
羅尼 你這是為什么呀 為什么
Why did you do it, Ronnie? Why?!
你明知道這樣不對
You knew it was wrong!
什么都別說
You mustn't say anything.
你要做什么
What do you want?
聰明的貓頭鷹什么都知道
Wise Owl knows best.
這是我妹妹的貓 米姆西
This is my sister's cat, Mimsy.
有一天它生病死了
One day he got poorly and died.
我跟她說別擔心 它去了貓的天堂
I told her not to worry and that he was in cat heaven now.
我不想讓它走
Don't want to let him go
我想讓它永遠留在我們身邊
I wish we could keep him for ever.
那是不可能的
But that's impossible.
傻瓜 傻瓜
Twit-you! Twit-you!
聰明的貓頭鷹
Wise Owl!
你怎么來了
What are you doing here?
孩子們 你們沒聽說過動物標本嗎
Have you children never heard of taxidermy?
動物什么
Taxi-what?
標本
Dermy.
就是一種把你最喜歡的寵物
It's a way of keeping your favourite pets
永遠留在身邊的方法
around for ever.
我教給你們看看
Let me show you.
你需要 手術刀 一些鍍鋅電線
You will need...A scalpel, some galvanised wire,
刮刀和化學染料
a scraper and tanning chemicals.
使用前務必一定要閱讀說明
Always read the label.
首先 你需要先把皮剝開
First, you need to peel the skin off.
在腿部和腹部周圍做切口
Make incisions around the legs and tummy.
然后慢慢的把動物皮從尸體上扯下來
Then pull the animal's pelt slowly from its carcass.
用手術刀摘掉眼睛
Then you remove the eyes with the scalpel.
這個我能幫上忙
I can do this for you.
然后在壁爐里焚化尸體
You can dispose of the body in an incinerator.
接著 把皮膚用化學染料浸泡一天時間
Next, use the chemicals to tan the skin for 24 hours.
這正是玩游戲或者吃三明治的好時刻
This is a good time to play a game or have a sandwich.
接下來 用泡沫做出個一樣大小的模型
Next, make a body shape from foam,
用鐵絲固定住 站著原地
using wire to keep it in place.
然后把染好顏色的皮
Then, pull the tanned hide
套在模型上
back onto the model.
就像往它皮里塞香腸一樣
Like putting a sausage into its skin!
正是如此
Exactly.
選個玻璃眼睛 以匹配你的寵物
Select glass eyes to match your pet's
輕輕的塞進模型的眼球里
and gently force them into the sockets.
適當調整其位置
Scrunch and pull it into position
用針線把所有東西重新縫好
and use a needle and thread to stitch everything back together
轉眼間
and, hey presto!
你知道怎么做后將變得很容易
Easy when you know how.
謝謝你 聰明的貓頭鷹
Thanks, Wise Owl.
它就和新的一樣
He's as good as new!
你好 我們改主意了
Yeah, we've had a change of heart
我想把法拉利帶回去
and I'd like to get Ferrari back, please,
不用做標本了
just as he was.
你還沒動手吧
You haven't touched him, have you?
真正的奧利弗先生在家嗎
Is the real Mr Oliver in?
我和鄰居聊過了
I were chatting to my neighbour
她說這家主人是個70多歲的老先生
and she said he's a gentleman in his 70s,
所以肯定不是你 對吧
so that's not you, is it?
那你是誰
So who are you, then?
你怎么會在這里
What are you even doing here?
你最好沒對它做什么
You'd better not have done anything to him.
誰
Who?
當然是法拉利
Ferrari!
我現在就要把它帶走
Now, can I have him back, please,
不然就要報警了
or am I going to have to call the police?
謝謝
Thank you.
我的天啊
Oh, dear God!
這是什么東西
What the hell do you call this?
太惡心了
It's disgusting!
你讓我怎么跟我女兒說
What am I going to tell my daughter now, eh?
她要是看到這個肯定會做噩夢的
She'll have bloody nightmares if she sees this!
該死的僵尸兔
Bloody Franken-rabbit!
你等著警察上門吧
You want reporting!
你這瘋子
You're sick!
死的本該是你 羅尼
It should have been you, Ronnie.
羅尼
Ronnie...
你好 爸爸
Hi, Dad.
給
Here.
你嚇了我一跳
You gave me quite a shock.
你得把修窗戶的錢給我
You'll have to give me the money for that window, you know.
喝吧
Cheers.
你不該喝這么多的
You shouldn't drink so much.
這才多少
It's only a nip.
我剛從皮克林回來
I've just come back from Pickering.
玩具博物館舉辦了
They had a '70s weekend
一場70年代的周末秀
at the toy museum.
去了不少像我這樣的老家伙
A few of the old buggers like me wheeled out.
雷·布魯克斯
Ray Brooks.
來自皮普金斯的奈杰爾
Nigel from Pipkins.
他是個笨家伙
One of the Bungles -
不過不嚇人
not the scary one.
我們玩得挺開心的
We had a laugh.
過去20多年
I don't suppose you've followed
你應該沒關注過我的工作吧
my career over the last 20-odd years?
你住的地方
Did they have a telly in...
有電視嗎
..where you were,
還是說他們不許你看電視呢
or were you not allowed?
《聰明的貓頭鷹》拍完之后
I didn't do much
我就沒做什么節目了
after Wise Owl finished.
有過幾次劇目巡演
Couple of theatre tours.
和杰夫·霍蘭德玩得不錯
Nice two-hander with Jeff Holland.
不過在那件事之后
Everything was a bit tainted after...
做什么都沒意思了
well, you know.
三四年前他們想做個重制版
They were thinking of bringing him back three or four years ago.
用電腦動畫 做出來也是垃圾
Computer animation. It would have been crap.
反正很不成功
Anyway, it all fizzled out, so...
所以我現在就做這個了
..I do this now.
你不會相信有多少人
You'd be surprised how many people
想要留住過去的東西
want to preserve something of the past,
留住一份記憶
keep a memory alive.
定格某個快樂的時刻
Freeze-frame of a happy moment.
我做過最大的標本是一只山羊
The biggest thing I've done is a goat.
花了我將近一個月的時間
I spent nearly a month on that.
有個小老太太帶著羊來找我
A little old lady brought him in.
她給羊取名叫潘
She called him Pan.
她也許是個女巫
Probably a witch.
不過我還從沒做過貓頭鷹的標本
Funnily enough, I've never done an owl.
我確實也不想做
I don't think I'd want to.
說說你在這里做什么
So, are you going to tell me what you're doing here?
是你媽讓你來的嗎
Did your mum put you up to it?
你知道周一是什么日子 對吧
You know what day Monday is, don't you?
周一
Monday?
哦 那件事
Oh. That.
她要是活著該有50歲了
She'd have been 50.
是嗎
Really?
時光如梭啊
Time flies.
我的信你收到過嗎
Did you get my letters?
收到過幾封
Yes, I had a few.
沒怎么看
I couldn't read half of them.
你的筆跡太潦草了
Your handwriting's shocking.
你就
Did you never...
你就從沒想回來看看我嗎
Did you never want to come and see me?
你媽不讓我回來
Your mother said not to.
她說我回來只會讓事情變得更糟
Said it would only make it worse.
反正是無法挽回了
It's all water under the bridge now anyway.
過來
Come here.
你不該再內疚了 明白嗎 羅尼
You mustn't feel guilty, you know, Ronnie.
那只是個意外
It was just an accident.
我并不怪你
I don't blame you,
不用擔心我的態度
if that's what you're worried about.
那天是我妹妹的生日
It was my sister's birthday.
我6歲了
I'm six!
她得到了一個娃娃
She got a doll,
一套茶具 還有一個風箏
a tea set and a kite.
現在就等媽媽回來
Now we're waiting for Mummy to come home
給她點生日蛋糕上的蠟燭了
so we can light the candles on her cake.
我現在就想點
I want to do it now.
我知道他們把火柴放在哪里了
I know where they keep the matches.
看
Look!
你不該玩火柴 喬安妮
You shouldn't play with matches, Joanne.
對吧 聰明的貓頭鷹
Isn't that right, Wise Owl?
聰明的貓頭鷹
Wise Owl?
怎么了
What?!
喬安妮想點蠟燭
Joanne wants to light her candles
可我告訴她這很危險
but I told her it's dangerous.
傻瓜
Twit-you!
火柴盒上不是寫了嗎
What does it say on the box?
你不會自己看嗎
Can't you read?
安全火柴
"Safety matches."
那不就行了
Exactly!
安全火柴很安全
They're safe.
她想點就讓她點吧
If she wants to light her candles, let her light them.
今天是她的生日
It's her birthday.
謝謝你 聰明的貓頭鷹
Thanks, Wise Owl.
你不等媽媽回來再說嗎
Are you sure we shouldn't wait for Mummy?
"Are you sure we shouldn't wait for Mummy?"
怎么什么事都要問別人
Why do you have to ask permission for everything?
你膽子太小了 羅尼 我的天啊
Grow some balls, Ronnie, for fuck's sake!
他說臟話
He said "balls".
可是
But...
別忘了 聰明的貓頭鷹總是對的
Wise Owl's always right, remember?
現在讓喬安妮許愿
Now, come on...let's leave Joanne to make her wish.
你跟我到樓上去
You're coming upstairs with me.
我想留在這里
I'd rather stay here.
聰明的貓頭鷹什么都知道
Wise Owl knows best.
然后呢
Now, what?
進去
In there.
坐下
Sit down.
羅尼
Ronnie...
你坐下
Sit...down!
為什么把責任推給我
Why did you let me take the blame?
好了 別糾結于過去了
Oh, let's not dredge up the past.
你說你在從酒吧回家的路上
You said you were on your way home from the pub
看到房子著火了
when you saw the house on fire.
你說你從窗戶爬進去救了我
You said you climbed in through a window and you rescued me.
你是英雄
You were the hero.
可你說謊了 對嗎
But that's not true, is it?
你就在房子里
You were in here.
和我在一起
With me.
你肯定是記錯了 兒子
I think you're remembering it wrong, son.
我沒記錯
I don't think so.
我還有事業呢
I had a career to protect.
我是公共信息影片公司的喉舌
I was the voice of the public information films
我女兒在火災中被活活燒死了
and my daughter gets burned alive in a fire.
這和我的形象很不符
Not very on brand, is it?
你說我該怎么辦
What was I supposed to do?
我信任你
I trusted you.
我一直很聽聰明貓頭鷹的話
I always did...everything...Wise Owl said.
那只是個游戲 羅尼
That was just a game, Ronnie.
沒什么不好的
It wasn't doing any harm.
你不也喜歡這游戲嗎
You enjoyed it.
我愛你
I loved you,
也愛喬安妮
and Joanne.
過來
Now...come on,
到我這兒來
come and join me.
別傻了
Don't be a twit-you.
給你老爸一個擁抱
Give your old man a hug.
別傷害我
Don't hurt me, please!
你還想陷入當年的處境嗎
Do you want to be put back in that place?
你住手 我就什么都不說
Stop this now and I won't say anything.
不
No.
我會說的
But I will.
羅尼
Ronnie!
羅尼 你什么意思
Ronnie! What did you mean?
你要去哪兒
Where are you going?
去找我媽
To see Mum.
把一切告訴她
I'm going to tell her.
告訴她什么呀
T-Tell her... Tell her what exactly?
真相
Everything.
不 不 今晚就算了
No, no, no. Stop the night here.
我們再談談
Let's just talk some more.
你不能去
You can't go.
羅尼 你什么都不能說
Ronnie! You mustn't say anything.
聰明的貓頭鷹不許你說
Wise Owl won't let you.
我們必須始終按聰明的貓頭鷹說的去做
And we must always do what Wise Owl says...
對嗎
..mustn't we?
不再是了
Not any more.
羅尼 你回來
Ronnie, stop!
傻瓜 傻瓜
Twit-you! Twit-you!
滾吧
Get stuffed.